As a matter of fact,
في الحقيقة،
I was trying to think about my career since I left the White House,
كنت أفكر في مستقبلي المهني منذ أن غادرت البيت الأبيض،
and the best example I have is a cartoon in The New Yorker a couple of years ago.
ويستحضرني مثال رائع وهو كرتون في مجلة (نيويورك) قبل سنتين
This little boy is looking up at his father,
وكان الولد ينظر إلى أبيه بإعجاب
and he says, "Daddy, when I grow up, I want to be a former president."
ويقول " أبي عندما أكبر أريد أن أصبح الرئيس الأسبق".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, I have had a great blessing as a former president,
في الواقع، كانت منفعة كبيرة لي أن أعمل رئيسا اسبق
because I have had an access
لأنني استطعت الوصول لكثير من الأماكن
that very few other people in the world have ever had
لم يحظى بها سوى القليل من الناس في هذا العالم
to get to know so many people around this whole universe.
والتعرف على كثير من الناس في هذا العالم الكبير.
Not only am I familiar with the 50 states in the United States,
و لستُ على معرفة فقط بالخمسين ولاية في أمريكا،
but also my wife and I have visited more than 145 countries in the world,
لكننى قمت مع زوجتي بزيارة أكثر من 145 بلدا في هذا العالم.
and the Carter Center has had full-time programs in 80 nations on Earth.
وكان لدى مركز(كارتر) برامج في أكثر من 80 بلد حول العالم.
And a lot of times, when we go into a country,
وفي كثير من الأحيان عندما كنا نزور بلدا ما
we not only the meet the king or the president,
كنا لانزور الرؤساء والملوك فحسب
but we also meet the villagers who live in the most remote areas of Africa.
بل كنا نلتقي بالقرويين الذين يقطنون المناطق النائية في إفريقيا،
So our overall commitment at the Carter Center
فكان التزامنا في مركز كارتر بشكل عام
is to promote human rights,
هو الترويج لحقوق الإنسان
and knowing the world as I do, I can tell you without any equivocation
ومعرفة العالم كما يجب ويمكنني إخباركم بشفافية
that the number one abuse of human rights on Earth
أن أسوأ انتهاك في العالم لحقوق الإنسان
is, strangely, not addressed quite often, is the abuse of women and girls.
هو انتهاك حقوق النساء والفتيات والغريب هو عدم التطرق لذلك بشكل كبير.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There are a couple of reasons for this that I'll mention to begin with.
وسأبدأ بذكر سببين لهذا الشيء
First of all is the misinterpretation of religious scriptures, holy scriptures,
أولاً، إساءة فهم النصوص الدينية المقدسة
in the Bible, Old Testament, New Testament, Quran and so forth,
مثل الإنجيل والعهد القديم والجديد والقرآن.
and these have been misinterpreted by men who are now in the ascendant positions
وهذه التفاسير الخاطئة قام بها رجال متحكمون
in the synagogues and the churches and in the mosques.
بالمعابد والكنائس والمساجد.
And they interpret these rules to make sure that women
ويقومون بتفسير هذه التعليمات حتى يجعلوا المرأة
are ordinarily relegated to a secondary position
في مكانة ثانوية بشكل إعتيادي
compared to men in the eyes of God.
مقارنةً مع الرجال من خلال نظرة دينية.
This is a very serious problem. It's ordinarily not addressed.
هذه مشكله خطيرة لم يتم التطرق لها بشكل كافٍ.
A number of years ago, in the year 2000,
فقبل عدة سنين وفي سنة 2000 تحديداً
I had been a Baptist, a Southern Baptist for 70 years --
كنت قد عملت مَعْمَدَانيّ لمدة 70 سنة في الكنيسة المعمدانية الجنوبية
I tell you, I still teach Sunday school every Sunday;
وأود أن أعلمكم أني مازلت أٌعلم كل يوم أحد،
I'll be teaching this Sunday as well --
وسأقوم بالتعليم الأحد القادم أيضاً.
but the Southern Baptist Convention in the year 2000 decided
ولكن قرر مؤتمر الكنيسة المعمدانية الجنوبية في سنة 2000،
that women should play a secondary position,
أن على النساء لعب أدوار ثانوية
a subservient position to men.
مقارنةً مع الرجال.
So they issued an edict, in effect,
وقد أصدروا قرارً،
that prevents women from being priests, pastors, deacons in the church,
يمنع المرأة من أن تصبح قسيسة في الكنيسة
or chaplains in the military,
أو حتى في الجيش.
and if a woman teaches a classroom
وإذا كانت المرأة تٌعلم في فصل دراسي هناك
in a Southern Baptist seminary,
في مركز تعليمي تابع للكنيسة ،
they cannot teach if a boy is in the room,
لا يحق لها التعليم إذا كان هناك ولد في الفصل.
because you can find verses in the Bible,
لأنك تجد آية في الأنجيل حول ذلك.
there's over 30,000 verses in the Bible,
يوجد أكثر من 3000 آية حول ذلك في الإنجيل،
that say that a woman shouldn't teach a man, and so forth.
تقول أن المرأة لايحق لها تعليم الرجال وهكذا.
But the basic thing is the scriptures are misinterpreted
لكن المشكلة الأساسية هي إساءة فهم النصوص الدينية،
to keep men in an ascendant position.
للمحافظة على الرجال بمكانة أعلى.
That is an all-pervasive problem,
وهذه مشكلة كبيرة حقاً.
because men can exert that power
لأنه بإمكان الرجال استخدام القوة في ذلك
and if an abusive husband or an employer, for instance, wants to cheat women,
وإذا أراد الرجل أو صاحب العمل غش المرأة مثلاً
they can say that if women are not equal in the eyes of God,
سيقولون إذا كات المرأة لا يحق لها أن تتساوى مع الرجل عند الله،
why should I treat them as equals myself?
فلما نعاملها بالمثل؟
Why should I pay them equal pay for doing the same kind of work?
لمَ ندفع للنساء نفس الأجر من أجل نفس العمل؟
The other very serious blight
والمفسدة الأخطر هنا
that causes this problem is the excessive resort to violence,
التي تسبب هذه المشكلة هي اللجوء إلى العنف بشكل متزايد
and that is increasing tremendously around the world.
وهذا يزداد بشكل مخيف حول العالم.
In the United States of America, for instance, we have had
في الولايات المتحدة على سبيل المثال،
an enormous increase in abuse of poor people,
كان هناك تزايد كبير في استغلال الفقراء
mostly black people and minorities, by putting them in prison.
وخاصةً السود والأقليات من خلال وضعهم في السجون.
When I was in office as governor of Georgia,
وعندما كنت في منصب حاكم (جورجيا)،
one out of every 1,000 Americans were in prison.
كان هناك واحد من ألف أمريكي في السجن.
Nowadays, 7.3 people per 1,000 are in prison.
لكن اليوم لدينا 7.3 من ألف في السجن
That's a sevenfold increase.
تلك زيادة بمقدار سبعة أضعاف.
And since I left the White House,
ومنذ مغادرتي للبيت الأبيض،
there's been an 800 percent increase in the number of women
أضحى لدينا زيادة 800%
who are black who are in prison.
من السجينات من النساء السود.
We also have [one of the only countries] on Earth
ولدينا أيضاً كدولة من ضمن القليل من دول العالم
that still has the death penalty that is a developed country.
عقوبة الإعدام في هذه الدولة المتقدمة.
And we rank right alongside the countries that are most abusive
ونقع بين أكثر الدول في انتهاك حقوق الإنسان
in all elements of human rights in encouraging the death penalty.
في كل المعايير من حيث التشجيع على عقوبة الإعدام.
We're in California now, and I figured out the other day
مازلنا في (كاليفورنيا) الآن وقد إكتشفت منذ زمن قريب
that California has spent four billion dollars
أن (كاليفورنيا) صرفت أربعة مليارات دولار
in convicting 13 people for the death penalty.
في الحكم على 13 شخص بعقوبة الإعدام.
If you add that up, that's 307 million dollars it costs California
إئا قمت بحساب ذلك فإن ولاية (كاليفورنيا) تتكلف 307 مليون دولار
to send a person to be executed.
من أجل تنفيذ حكم إعدام في حق شخص واحد.
Nebraska this week just passed a law abolishing the death penalty,
وقد قامت ولاية (نبراسكا) بإصدار قانون لإلغاء عقوبة الإعدام هذا الأسبوع،
because it costs so much. (Applause)
لأنها مكلفة جداً. (تصفيق)
So the resort to violence and abuse of poor people and helpless people
لذا فإن اللجوء إالى العنف واستغلال الفقراء و الضعفاء
is another cause of the increase in abuse of women.
هو سبب آخر لإستغلال المرأة.
Let me just go down a very few abuses of women that concern me most,
دعوني هنا أستعرض بعض أنواع الإستغلال بحق النساء التي تقلقني حقاً،
and I'll be fairly brief, because I have a limited amount of time, as you know.
وسأحاول اختصار ذلك بسبب ضيق الوقت، كما تعلمون
One is genital mutilation.
أولاً، تشويه الأعضاء التناسلية للإناث أو الختان.
Genital mutilation is horrible and not known by American women,
الختان شيء مروع، لكنه غير معروف للنساء في الولايات المتحدة.
but in some countries, many countries,
ولكن في كثير من الدول،
when a child is born that's a girl, very soon in her life,
وفي مرحلة أولية من عمر الفتيات،
her genitals are completely cut away by a so-called cutter
يقومون بعملية الختان لهم بما يسمى القاطع الحاد،
who has a razor blade and, in a non-sterilized way,
موصول بشفرة حادة ومن غير تعقيم،
they remove the exterior parts of a woman's genitalia.
يقومون بأزالة الأجزاء الخارجية للأعضاء التناسلية عند الفتاة.
And sometimes, in more extreme cases but not very rare cases,
وفي حالات قليلة وغريبة، يقومون بخياطة فتحة المهبل
they sew the orifice up so the girl can just urinate or menstruate.
بحيث تتمكن الفتاة من التبول و الحيض الشهري فقط،
And then later, when she gets married, the same cutter goes in
وعندما تتزوج يستخدمون نفس القاطع
and opens the orifice up so she can have sex.
من أجل فتح المهبل بحيث تتمكن الفتاة من ممارسة الجنس.
This is not a rare thing, although it's against the law in most countries.
وهذا ليس بشيءً نادر مع أنه ضد القانون في معظم البلدان.
In Egypt, for instance,
في مصر على سبيل المثال،
91 percent of all the females that live in Egypt today
91% من الإناث اليوم هناك،
have been sexually mutilated in that way.
تم ختانهم بنفس الطريقة.
In some countries, it's more than 98 percent
وفي بعض البلدان يوجد أكثر من 98% من النساء،
of the women are cut that way before they reach maturity.
تم ختانهم قبل وصولهم سن البلوغ.
This is a horrible affliction
إنه شيءً محزن فعلاً،
on all women that live in those countries.
ما يحدث للنساء في تلك البلدان.
Another very serious thing is honor killings,
وهناك شيء آخر مخيف هو "قتل الشرف".
where a family with misinterpretation, again, of a holy scripture --
وهنا يكون لدى العائلة سوء فهم عن النصوص الدينية.
there's nothing in the Quran that mandates this --
حيث أنه لايوجد شيء في القرآن
will execute a girl in their family
يتبنى قتل فتاة من قبل عائلتها.
if she is raped
إذا ماكانت تلك الفتاة مغتصبة
or if she marries a man that her father does not approve,
أو تزوجت رجل دون موافقة أبيها
or sometimes even if she wears inappropriate clothing.
وأحياناً حتى خروجها بملابس غير مقبولة.
And this is done by members of her own family,
ويتم هذا العمل من قبل أحد أفراد عائلتها،
so the family becomes murderers
لتتحول عائلتها إلى قتلة
when the girl brings so-called disgrace to the family.
إذا ماقامت تلك الفتاة بإحضار مايسمى "العار" إلى عائلتها.
An analysis was done in Egypt not so long ago by the United Nations
وكان هناك تحليل أجري في مصر من قبل الأمم المتحدة منذ فترة قصيرة،
and it showed that 75 percent of these murders of a girl
يوضح أن 75% من حالات القتل للفتيات هذه
are perpetrated by the father, the uncle or the brother,
قام بها الأب أو العم أو الأخ،
but 25 percent of the murders are conducted by women.
ولكن 25% من حالات القتل قام بها نساء.
Another problem that we have in the world
مشكلة أخرى في هذا العالم،
that relates to women particularly is slavery,
تخص النساء هي العبودية
or human trafficking it's called nowadays.
أو التجارة بالبشر بحسب التسمية الحديثة.
There were about 12.5 million people sold from Africa into slavery
وكان قد بيع 12.5 مليون شخص في إفريقيا كعبيد
in the New World back in the 19th century and the 18th century.
في القرن التاسع عشر والثامن عشر من العصر الحديث.
There are 30 million people now living in slavery.
الآن يوجد 30 مليون شخص يعيشون في العبودية.
The United States Department of State now has a mandate from Congress
كُلّفت وزارة الخارجية الأمريكية من قبل الكونغرس
to give a report every year,
بإصدار تقرير سنوي عن هذا الشيء،
and the State Department reports that 800,000 people are sold
ويشير تقرير الخارجية الأمريكية إلى أن 800 ألف شخص
across international borders every year into slavery,
يتم بيعهم سنوياُ عبر الحدود الدولية كعبيد،
and that 80 percent of those sold are women,
وأن 80% منهم هم نساء،
into sexual slavery.
من أجل العبودية الجنسية.
In the United States right this moment,
وفي الولايات المتحدة حالياً،
60,000 people are living in human bondage, or slavery.
هناك 60 ألف شخص يعيشون في العبودية.
Atlanta, Georgia, where the Carter Center is located
ولايات (أتلانتا وجورجيا) حيث يقع مقر مركز (كارتر)
and where I teach at Emory University,
وحيث أقوم بالتدريس في جامعة (أيموري)
they have between 200 and 300 women, people sold into slavery every month.
يوجد 200 إلى 300 إمرأة تباع للعبودية كل شهر،
It's the number one place in the nation because of that.
مما يجعله المكان الأول في تلك في البلاد.
Atlanta has the busiest airport in the world,
(أتلانتا) يوجد فيها أكثر مطار مزدحم في العالم،
and they also have a lot of passengers that come from the Southern Hemisphere.
والكثير من الركاب يأتي من نصف الكرة الجنوبي .
If a brothel owner
وإذا أراد صاحب محل بغاء
wants to buy a girl that has brown or black skin,
شراء فتاة صاحبة بشرة سمراء،
they can do it for 1,000 dollars.
يمكن ذلك بألف دولار.
A white-skinned girl brings several times more than that,
وبالنسبة للبنت صاحبة البشرة البيضاء تكلف أكثر من ذلك بأضعاف،
and the average brothel owner in Atlanta and in the United States now
و صاحب محل الدعارة في (أتلانتا) في الولايات المتحدة اليوم،
can earn about $35,000 per slave.
يمكنه جني 35 ألف دولار من كل حالة عبودية.
The sex trade in Atlanta, Georgia, exceeds the total drug trade in Atlanta, Georgia.
تجارة الجنس في ولايتي أتلانتا وجورجيا تفوق كامل تجارة المخدرات فيهم.
So this is another very serious problem, and the basic problem is prostitution,
إذاً هذه مشكلة أخرى خطيرة والمشكلة الأساسية هي الدعارة،
because there's not a whorehouse in America
حيث أنه لا يوجد بيت دعارة في أمريكا
that's not known by the local officials,
لايعرفه المسؤولون المحليون،
the local policemen, or the chief of police or the mayor and so forth.
والشرطة المحلية وقائد الشرطة والمحافظ وآخرون.
And this leads to one of the worst problems,
وهذا يقودنا إلى أسوأ مشكلة،
and that is that women are bought increasingly and put into sexual slavery
هو أن النساء تُشترى وتوضع في العبودية الجنسية
in all countries in the world.
بشكل متزايد في كل أنحاء العالم.
Sweden has got a good approach to it.
السويد لها توجّه جيّد نحو ذلك،
About 15 to 20 years ago, Sweden decided to change the law,
فقبل حوالي 15 إلى 20 سنة قامت السويد بتغيير القانون،
and women are no longer prosecuted
فلم تعد النساء تُحاكم
if they are in sexual slavery,
إذا كانوا في حالة العبودية الجنسية
but the brothel owners and the pimps and the male customers are prosecuted,
ولكن صاحب بيت الدعارة والقوادون والزبائن من الرجال هم من تتمّ مُحاكمتهم،
and -- (Applause) -- prostitution has gone down.
(تصفيق) انخفضت نسبة الدعارة.
In the United States, we take just the opposite position.
في الولايات المتحدة يوجد لدينا النقيض لذلك.
For every male arrested for illegal sex trade,
حيث أن كل رجل يُعتقل بتجارة الجنس بشكل غير شرعي،
25 women are arrested in the United States of America.
يُعتقل هناك 25 إمرأة.
Canada, Ireland, I've already said Sweden,
كندا، ايرلندا، وذكرت السويد مسبقاً،
France, and other countries are moving now towards this so-called Swedish model.
وفرنسا وبلدان أخرى تخطو نحو النموذج السويدي.
That's another thing that can be done.
هذا شيء آخر يمكن عمله.
We have two great institutions in this country that all of us admire:
لدينا مؤسستين عظيمتين في بلدنا الكل يحترمهم:
our military and our great university system.
الجيش والنظام الجامعي الرائع.
In the military, they are now analyzing how many sexual assaults take place.
في الجيش يقومون بتحليل كم أعتداء جنسي حدث.
The last report I got, there were 26,000 sexual assaults
وآخر تقرير حصلت عليه، ذكر حدوث 26 ألف اعتداء جنسي
that took place in the military --
من قبل الجيش،
26,000.
ستة وعشرون ألف!
Only 3,000, not much more than 1 percent, are actually prosecuted,
فقط 3 ألف، هذا ليس بكثير، أكثر من 1% يحاكمون في الواقع
and the reason is that the commanding officer of any organization --
والسبب هو أن الضابط السؤول في أي مؤسسة
a ship like my submarine, or a battalion in the Army
على سبيل المثال، سفينة أو كتيبة في الجيش
or a company in the Marines --
أو شركة تعمل في البحرية،
the commanding officer has the right under law to decide
الضابط المسؤول لديه الحق قانونياً أن يقرر
whether to prosecute a rapist or not,
محاكمة المغتصب من عدمها،
and of course, the last thing they want is for anybody to know
وطبعاً، آخر مايريدونه هو أن يعرف الناس
that under their command, sexual assaults are taking place,
حدوث أعتداءات جنسية حصلت تحت أمرتهم،
so they do not do it.
فهم لن يقوموا بالمحاكمة.
That law needs to be changed.
لذا يجب تغيير ذلك القانون.
About one out of four girls who enter American universities
واحدة من أربع فتيات تدخل الجامعات الأمريكية
will be sexually assaulted before she graduates,
تتعرض لاعتداء جنسي قبل التخرج،
and this is now getting a lot of publicity,
وهذا أصبح معروفً بشكل كبير الآن،
partially because of my book, but other things,
بسبب كتابي نسبياً وبسبب أمور أخرى،
and so 89 universities in America are now condemned
أُدينت 89 جامعة في أمريكا
by the Department of Education under Title IX
من قبل وزارة التعليم تحت قانون عدم التمييز (IX)
because the officials of the universities are not taking care of the women
لأن المسؤولون في الجامعات لايهتمون بالنساء،
to protect them from sexual assault.
من أجل حمايتهم من الاعتدءات الجنسية.
The Department of Justice says that more than half of the rapes
وتقول وزارة العدل، أن أكثر من نصف حالات الاغتصاب في الحرم الجامعي
on a college campus take place by serial rapists,
يقوم بها مغتصبون متسلسلون
because outside of the university system,
بسبب القانون خارج الجامعة،
if they rape somebody, they'll be prosecuted,
إذا اغتصبوا أحد سيقومون بمحاكمتهم،
but when they get on a university campus, they can rape with impunity.
لكن في الحرم الجامعي يوجد حصانة للمغتصب.
They're not prosecuted.
ولن يقوم أحد بمحاكمتهم.
Those are the kinds of things that go on in our society.
هذا مايحدث داخل مجتمعنا.
Another thing that's very serious about the abuse of women and girls
و شيءً آخر خطير جداً حول استغلال النساء
is the lack of equal pay for equal work,
هو نقص تكافئ أجور العمل،
as you know. (Applause)
كما أنكم تعلمون (تصفيق)
And this is sometimes misinterpreted, but for full-time employment,
ولكن أحياناُ يكون هناك إساءة فهم فالعمل بدوام كامل،
a woman in the United States now gets 23 percent less than a man.
تحصل المرأة في الولايات المتحدة على 23% أقل من الرجل.
When I became president, the difference was 39 percent.
عندما كنت رئيٍساً كان الفارق 39%.
So we've made some progress, partially because I was president
لذا حققنا تقدما جزئياً عندما كنت رئيساً
and so forth -- (Applause) (Laughter) --
(تصفيق) (ضحك)
but in the last 15 years, there's been no progress made,
في الـ 15 سنة الأخيرة لم يكن هناك تقدم،
so it's been just about 23 or 24 percent difference
فكانت النسبة حول 23% أو 24 %
for the last 15 years.
في 15 سنة الأخيرة.
These are the kind of things that go on.
هذا مايحدث
If you take the Fortune 500 companies,
إذا أخذت كمثال الـ 500 شركة الأغنى،
23 of them have women CEOs,
23 منهم لديهم الرئيس التنفيذي إمرأة،
out of 500,
من 500 شركة،
and those CEOs, I need not tell you,
ويجب أن أعلمكم أن الرئيسات التنفيذيات
make less on an average
يصنعون أقل من المتوسط
than the other CEOs.
من الرؤساء الأخرين.
Well, that's what goes on in our country.
حسناً، هذا ما يجري في بلدنا.
Another problem with the United States
ومشكلة أخرى لدى الولايات المتحدة،
is we are the most warlike nation on Earth.
هي أننا أكثر دولة لديها حروب في العالم .
We have been to war with about 25 different countries
فقد حاربنا حوالي 25 بلدا،
since the Second World War.
منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية.
Sometimes, we've had soldiers on the ground fighting.
أحياناً يكون لدينا جنود تقاتل على الأرض.
The other times, we've been flying overhead
وأحياناً أخرى تطير فوق روؤس الناس
dropping bombs on people.
وتلقي القنابل على الناس.
Other times, of course, now, we have drones that attack people and so forth.
وأحيانأً أخرى لدينا طائرات بدون طيار تهاجم الناس وهكذا.
We've been at war with 25 different countries
فقد حاربنا حوالي 25 بلدا
or more since the Second World War.
أو أكثر منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية.
There was four years, I won't say which ones,
كان هناك فترة أربع سنوات لن أحددها،
where we didn't --
لم نقم ب...
(Applause) -- we didn't drop a bomb, we didn't launch a missile,
(تصفيق) لم نلق قنبلة ولم نطلق صاروخ.
we didn't fire a bullet.
ولم نطلق طلقة واحدة.
But anyway, those kinds of things, the resort to violence
لكن اللجوء للعنف،
and the misinterpretation of the holy scriptures
هو سوء فهم للنصوص الدينية.
are what causes, are the basic causes, of abuse of women and girls.
هذا هو السبب الرئيسي لاستغلال النساء والفتيات
There's one more basic cause that I need not mention,
يوجد سبب آخر، لم أذكره،
and that is that in general, men don't give a damn.
هو أن الرجال لا يكترثون لذلك،
(Applause) That's true.
(تصفيق) هذه هي الحقيقة.
The average man that might say, I'm against the abuse of women and girls
الرجل العادي قد يقول أنه ضد التمييز ضد المرأة
quietly accepts the privileged position that we occupy,
لكنه يصمت ويقبل بوضعه الجيد.
and this is very similar to what I knew when I was a child,
وهذا شبيه بما عرفته في طفولتي،
when separate but equal had existed.
عندما وجد نظام الفصل العنصري.
Racial discrimination, legally, had existed for 100 years,
التمييز العنصري وجد منذ مائة سنة،
from 1865 at the end of the War Between the States, the Civil War,
منذ 1865 في نهاية الحرب الأهلية بين الولايات نفسها،
all the way up to the 1960s,
وحتى الستينات من القرن العشرين،
when Lyndon Johnson got the bills passed
عندما مرر (ليدون جونسون) مشروع قوانين
for equal rights.
من أجل المساواة في الحقوق.
But during that time, there were many white people
و لكن خلال تلك الفترة كان هناك كثير من السكان البيض،
that didn't think that racial discrimination was okay,
الذين لم يوافقوا على التمييز العنصري،
but they stayed quiet,
لكنهم بقيوا صامتين،
because they enjoyed the privileges of better jobs,
لأنهم كانو يتمتعون بمزايا كبيرة، وظائف أفضل،
unique access to jury duty,
وصول مميز إلى القضاء،
better schools, and everything else,
ومدارس أفضل و كل شيء آخر.
and that's the same thing that exists today,
نفس الشيء يوجد اليوم،
because the average man really doesn't care.
لأن الرجل العادي لايهتم،
Even though they say, "I'm against discrimination against girls and women,"
مع أنهم يقولون أنني ضد التمييز ضد المرأة،
they enjoy a privileged position.
هم يستمتعون بمناصب عالية
And it's very difficult to get the majority of men
ومن الصعب إحضار كل الرجال
who control the university system,
الذين يسيطرون على النظام الجامعي،
the majority of men that control the military system,
والغالبية من الرجال الذين يتحكمون بالمؤسسة العسكرية
the governments of the world,
والأغلبية من الرجال الذين يتحكمون بحكومات العالم
and the majority of men that control the great religions.
والغالبية من الرجال الذين يتحكمون بالأديان العظيمة.
So what is the basic thing that we need to do today?
إذاً ماذا يجب أن نفعل الآن؟
I would say the best thing that we could do today
أقول لكم أفضل شيء ممكن فعله اليوم هو،
is for the women in the powerful nations
هو أن النساء في البلدان المتقدمة،
like this one, and where you come from,
مثل هذا البلد ومثل بلدانكم
Europe and so forth, who have influence and who have freedom to speak and to act,
الذين لديهم تأثير وحرية التعبير،
need to take the responsibility on yourselves
عليهم تحمل العاتق على أنفسهم
to be more forceful in demanding
و أن يطلبوا بشكل أقوى
an end to racial discrimination against girls and women
إنهاء التمييز ضد النساء والفتيات
all over the world.
في جميع أنحاء العالم.
The average woman in Egypt
المرأة العادية في مصر
doesn't have much to say about her daughters
لايمكنها الدفاع عن بناتها
getting genitally mutilated and so forth.
لمنع حصولهم على الختان وأمور أخرى.
I didn't even go down to detail about that.
لم أتطرق بعد إلى التفاصيل حول ذلك.
But I hope that out of this conference,
لكن آمل ذلك في هذا المؤتمر،
that every woman here will get your husbands to realize
أن تجعل كل مرأة هنا زوجها يدرك،
that these abuses on the college campuses and the military and so forth
أن حالات الإستغلال هذه في الحرم الجامعي وفي الجيش
and in the future job market,
وفي مستقبل العمل،
need to protect your daughters and your granddaughters.
عليكم حماية بناتكم وحفيداتكم.
I have 12 grandchildren, four children, and 10 great-grandchildren,
وأنا لدي 12 حفيد و4 أولاد و 10 أبناء أحفادي،
and I think often about them
وعادةً ما أفكر بهم،
and about the plight that they will face in America,
وعن المشكلة التي سيواجهونها في المستقبل،
not only if they lived in Egypt or a foreign country,
ليس فقط بالنسبة للعيش في مصر أو بلد أجنبي،
in having equal rights,
في الحصول على حقوق متساوية،
and I hope that all of you will join me
وأمل منكم أن تنضموا إلي،
in being a champion for women and girls around the world
وأن نكون أبطال من أجل الأطفال والنساء حول العالم،
and protect their human rights.
ونحمي حقوقهم كبشر.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)